I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that by age 50
about half of all men and women
will experience hair loss?
The majority of age-related
hair loss is genetic,
but even identical twins can have
dramatically different heads of hair
based on their diet and lifestyle.
In our first story, we look at whether
biotin or zinc supplements
have any role in
preventing hair loss.
“Studies show that by age 50,
approximately half of men and women
will experience hair loss.”
No, it’s not caused by
washing your hair too much,
or brushing your hair too little,
two of the many myths out there.
The majority of hair
loss with age is genetic
for both women and men,
in the case of this study.
Based on twin studies, the
heritability of baldness in men
is 79 percent, meaning about
80 percent of the differences
in hair loss between men
is genetically determined.
But that still leaves some wiggle room.
Even if you have identical
twins, identical twin sisters
in this case with the same DNA,
one can have more hair loss
than the other thanks to Increased stress,
increased smoking, having more children,
or having a history of high
blood pressure or cancer.
Smoking can contribute to
the development of both
male and female pattern baldness
because of the genotoxic compounds
in cigarettes may damage
the DNA in hair follicles
and cause microvascular poisoning
in the base of the follicle.
Other toxic agents associated with
hair loss include mercury,
because it seems to concentrate about
250-fold in growing scalp hair.
In fact, maybe the reason
Shakespeare started losing his hair
was due to mercury poisoning
fromsyphilis treatment.
Thankfully doctors don’t
give people mercury anymore.
These days, as the CDC points out,
mercury mainly enters the body
through seafood consumption.
So, doctors should consider
screening for mercury toxicity
when they see hair loss, since there’s
something we can do about it.
Instructing patients to reduce
fish intake and repeat blood tests
could offer relief of symptoms
and uncover dietary habits
that may be a source of heavy
metal-induced hair loss.
Though admittedly, sometimes heavy
metal can lead to too much hair.
What about nutrient deficiencies
as a cause of hair loss?
After bariatric surgery, the most
frequent nutrient deficiency symptom
is hair loss, but that’s
because they’ve had their anatomy
rearranged to cause
malabsorption on purpose.
In general, there is little
evidence to suggest that vitamin
and mineral supplementation
benefits people
unless they are actually deficient.
For example, we’ve known
for centuries that scurvy,
severe vitamin C deficiency,
can cause hair loss,
but once you have
enough vitamin C such that
our gums aren’t bleeding,
there’s no data correlating
vitamin C levels and hair loss once you have
a certain baseline sufficiency of vitamin C.
It’s also a myth that
supplements containing zinc
will increase hair growth,
unless you have zinc deficiency,
like if you’re an alcoholic or something.
But if you have normal zinc levels
in your blood, taking more zinc
won’t help, and in fact can
have negative side effects.
It’s the same thing with
taking iron supplements.
The most common ingredient in
top-selling hair loss products
is vitamin B7, also known as biotin.
Yes, biotin deﬁciency causes hair loss,
but there are no evidence-based data
that supplementing biotin
promotes hair growth.
And severe biotin deﬁciency
in healthy individuals eating
a normal diet has never been reported,
but if you eat raw egg whites,
you can acquire a biotin deﬁciency
since there are these
compounds that attach to biotin
and prevent it from being absorbed.
But other than rare deficiency syndromes,
it’s a myth that biotin
supplements increase hair growth.
But hey, why not just have the
attitude "can’t hurt, might help?”
Because of the lack
of regulatory oversight
of the supplement industry
and, in the case of biotin,
interference with lab tests.
Many dietary supplements
promoted for hair health
contain biotin levels up to 650 times
the recommended daily intake of biotin.
And excess biotin in the
blood can play haywire on a bunch
of different blood tests,
including thyroid function,
other hormone tests
including pregnancy),
and the test they do to see
if you’ve had a heart attack,
so it could potentially
even be life or death
And in terms of poor regulation,
as I’ve done tons of videos about,
there are all sorts of supplement
manufacturer shenanigans.
For example, this outbreak
in which hundreds suffered
selenium toxicity because
they had an oopsie
and put 200 times the dose and
so it ended up causing hair loss.
And the same thing can happen
with getting too much vitamin A.
Next up, we look at
the pros and cons
of the drugs finasteride
and minoxidil for hair loss.
“Any consumer looking on the
Internet for a treatment
for hair loss is exposed to
a multitude of remedies.”
However, we only have good
evidence for efficacy for the
FDA-approved drugs,
finasteride, sold as Propecia,
and minoxidil, sold as Rogaine.
It’s considered a myth that all
the patented hair-loss supplements
on the market will increase hair growth.
And they may actually be more expensive,
with over-the-counter supplement
regimens costing up to more
than a thousand dollars a year,
whereas the drugs may only
be one to three hundred dollars.
The drugs can help but
can cause side-effects.
The Propecia can diminish libido
and cause sexual disfunction,
while the topical Minoxidil
can cause itching.
To understand why there are
so many hormonal side-effects
for Propecia like impotence, testicular
pain, and breast enlargement,
you have to understand how the drug works.
Androgens, male hormones like testosterone,
are the principal drivers of hair
growth in both men and women.
We know this from studies
a half century ago
that show that castration
of men stopped hair loss.
Why exactly were they being castrated?
Due to eugenics laws in the United States,
when mentally handicapped
persons were castrated
or had their tubes tied against their will.
So-called retarded persons
were routinely sterilized
without their consent or knowledge and we,
the United States of America, was
the first country to introduce
eugenic laws, which were later
upheld by the US Supreme Court.
In the 1930s, a vocal
proponent complained that
“The Germans are beating
us at our own game.”
Anyway, testosterone is the primary
androgen circulating in the blood
and can be converted to
dihydrotestosterone,
which is even more powerful by an
enzyme called 5-alpha reductase.
That’s the enzyme that's
blocked by Propecia,
so it inhibits the souping
up of testosterone.
That’s why women are
not supposed to take it
since it could femininize male fetuses;
whereas for men it has
the sexual side effects
like erectile dysfunction, which
can affect men for years.
It’s something the drug companies
had to disclose for the last decade:
“a difﬁculty in achieving an erection
that continues after
stopping the medication,”
side effects that may even be permanent.
Up to 20 percent of subjects
reporting persistent sexual dysfunction
for six or more years
after stopping the drug,
suggesting the possibility
that it may never go away.
What we think might be
happening is that the drug
may actually structurally
change the part of your brain
responsible for sexual function.
And indeed, though blood
levels of hormones in users
with persistent effects appear normal.
If you do a spinal tap and look at the
cerebrospinal fluid surrounding their brains,
neurosteroid levels do appear
to end up being altered.
So, it's "recommended that
prescribers of ﬁnasteride,
as well as potential users, be
aware of the potential serious
long-term risks of a medication
used for a cosmetic purpose.”
To date, no new interventions
are used routinely
in the treatment of male or
female pattern baldness.
Given the side-effects of
the current drug options,
there is a need for alternative treatments.
So, what about foods? Things we
could eat to combat hair loss.
That’s exactly what we’re
going to explore next.
Androgenic or androgenetic
alopecia, also known as
male or female pattern hair loss,
is one of the most common
chronic problems seen by dermatologists.
Wait, so it’s called male pattern hair loss
and female pattern hair loss?
Yeah, in men they call it
male pattern hair loss,
and in women they call it
female pattern hair loss.
Okay. Either way, it is characterized
by progressive hair loss,
predominantly of the central scalp.
I’ve talked about
hair loss supplements.
I’ve talked about hair loss drugs.
What about foods for hair loss?
What role might diet play in
the treatment of hair loss?
Human experiments with fecal transplants
offer a clue to how powerful
our microbiome is, with reports
of improvements in hair loss
after a fecal slurry made from freshly
passed stools from a donor
was administered into another person’s
colon, and not just by a little.
A totally bald guy starts
growing back hair a few months
after a fecal transplant and
a little over a year later,
check it out, completely regrown.
The moral of the story is
not to drink brown smoothies,
but to keep your good gut bugs happy.
Population studies have
found that male pattern baldness
is associated with poor sleeping habits
and the consumption of meat and junk food;
whereas protective associations were found
for the consumption of raw
vegetables, fresh herbs,
as well as the frequent
consumption of soymilk.
Drinking soy beverages on a
weekly basis was associated
with 62 percent lower odds of
moderate to severe hair loss,
raising the possibility
that there may be
compounds in plants
that may be protective.
Complementary and alternative
medicine treatments
“boast the ability to
’cure’ hair loss ‘safely’
with ‘less side effects’
than conventional medicine.
However, it is important...to look
beyond the overarching claims
and marketing to critically
review the literature.”
For example, many studies
have little relevance
because the evidence was
obtained on shaved rodents.
Hey, let’s smear shaved
mice with bee venom.
And even when they do clinical
studies on actual people,
sometime there’s no placebo
control; so, you have no idea
if the food had anything to do with it.
But there has been a randomized
double-blind, placebo-controlled study
of compounds in hot peppers and soy,
showing significantly higher
promotion of hair growth.
Here are some before-and-after
pictures of both men and women.
Okay, but what kind of
doses were they using?
6 mg of capsaicin a day and
75 milligrams of isoflavones.
Okay, what does that
translate out to in real food?
You can get 6 mg of capsaicin
in just a quarter
of a fresh jalapeno pepper a day.
That sounds pretty doable.
And you can get 75 mg of isoflavones
eating ¾ of a cup of tempeh
or just straight soybeans.
Soy nuts are even
more concentrated,
dry roasted soybeans,
but given the formation of
advanced glycation end-products
in high fat/high protein foods at
high temperatures, I’d suggest
avoiding routinely eating roasted or
toasted nuts, seeds, or soy.
There’s also been a
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of pumpkin seed oil.
Where did they get that idea?
In 2009, a study out of South Korea
found that randomizing men
with BPH—enlarged prostate glands—
to just 320 mg of pumpkin seed oil
a day (that’s about 16th of a teaspoon,
so just a few drops a day)
improved urinary flow rates.
Urinary flow continued to kink off
and decline in the control group,
but those taking the equivalent
of just like eating two
single pumpkin seeds a day saw
a significant improvement.
That would seem to be
an anti-androgen effect,
so maybe it would help with hair loss.
It seems to work in mice
when used topically,
but what about in people
just eating pumpkin seeds.
It couldn’t hurt.
Sadly, we often throw away
pumpkin seeds, squash seeds,
or watermelon seeds, and
they actually have
a rich repertoire of nutrition.
But you don’t know if they
actually work for hair loss,
until you put it to the test.
In a study, 76 men with male
pattern baldness received
400 mg of pumpkin seed oil
a day hidden in capsules,
or they took capsules instead of
the placebo for a few months.
Again, that’s only like eating
two pumpkin seeds a day,
maybe two and a half pumpkin seeds.
They measured scalp hair growth
with all sorts of objective
and subjective measures, and...
after 24 weeks of treatment,
self-rated improvement
and satisfaction scores
in the actual pumpkin seed
oil group was higher,
and they objectively had more
hair, a 40 percent increase
in hair counts compared to only
10 percent in the placebo group.
In the pumpkin group, 95 percent
remained either unchanged or improved,
whereas in the control
group more than 90 percent
remained unchanged or worsened.
Given such a pronounced
effect might we be worried
about sexual side-effects?
They looked before and after at
an index of erectile dysfunction
and found no evidence
of adverse effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.